Guide to the Tamiment Library Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Collection TAM.507
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.), 2007-present
  - Industrial Workers of the World, Feb 2007-present
    The Industrial Workers of the World, founded in 1905, is a member-run union for all workers, dedicated to organizing on the job, in industries and communities. IWW members are organizing to win better conditions and build a world with economic democracy. IWW works to change the atmosphere in workplaces run for the benefit of workers and communities. The IWW contends that all workers should be united as a class and that the wage system should be abolished. They may be best known for the Wobbly Shop model of workplace democracy, in which workers elect recallable delegates, and other norms of grassroots democracy (self-management) are implemented.
  - International Alliance of Theatrical and Stage Employees, Local 52, Feb 2009-present
    International Alliance of Theatrical and Stage Employees, Local 52 was founded in the early 1920s, and was officially chartered by the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees (IATSE) in 1924. The local’s jurisdiction includes, New York, New Jersey, Delaware, Pennsylvania (with the exception of Pittsburgh), and Connecticut. The labor union represents technicians, artisans and craftspeople in the entertainment industry, including live theatre, motion picture and television production, and trade shows.
  - International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees, Moving Picture Technicians, Artists and Allied Crafts of the United States, Its Territories and Canada (IATSE), Dec 2009-present
    The International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees, Moving Picture Technicians, Artists and Allied Crafts of the United States, Its Territories and Canada was originally chartered by the American Federation of Labor as the National Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees in 1893. With 110,000 members, the labor union represents technicians, artisans and craftspeople in the entertainment industry, including live theatre, motion picture and television production, and trade shows.
  - International Association of Bridge, Structural, Ornamental and Reinforcing Iron Workers (Ironworkers), Dec 2009-present
    The International Association of Bridge, Structural, Ornamental and Reinforcing Iron Workers Union, AFL-CIO, founded in 1896, represents primarily construction workers, as well as shipbuilding and metal fabrication employees. The current membership stands at approximately 140,000, with 15,000 apprentices.
  - International Association of Fire Fighters (IAFF), Dec 2009-present
    The International Association of Fire Fighters (IAFF), found in 1918 and headquartered in Washington, DC, represents more than 295,000 full-time professional fire fighters and paramedics who protect 85 percent of the nation’s population. More than 3,100 affiliates and their members protect communities in every state in the United States and in Canada. The IAFF is one of the most active lobbying organizations in Washington; its Political Action Committee, FIREPAC, is among the top 25 federal PACs among the more than 4,000 in the country.
  - International Association of Heat and Frost Insulators and Allied Workers, Dec 2009-present
    International Association of Heat and Frost Insulators and Allied Workers, was formerly known as the International Association of Heat and Frost Insulators and Asbestos Workers. One of the major jobs of the members of the union has long been the safe removal of hazardous asbestos-containing materials, which were previously used in many construction products, such as insulation, adhesives, caulks, and flooring tiles. The object of the International Association of Heat and Frost Insulators and Allied Workers is to assist its membership in securing employment, to defend their rights and advance their interests as working men and women, and by education and cooperation, raise them to that position in society to which they are justly entitled.
  - International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers (IAM), Dec 2009-present
    The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, founded in 1888, is an AFL-CIO/CLC trade union representing approx. 646,933 workers as of 2006 in more than 200 industries, The union represents machinists, aerospace, and transportation workers.
  - International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers and Helpers, Dec 2009-present
    The International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers and Helpers, organized in 1880, represents 100,000 workers in heavy industry, shipbuilding, manufacturing, railroads, cement, mining, and related industries. The Boilermakers union has a four-year apprenticeship training program. Boilermakers primarily work in nuclear and fossil power plants. However they also work in shipyards, refineries and chemical plants. The work involves welding, rigging and fabricating. All work done is governed by OSHA (Occupational Safety and Health Administration) or MSHA (Mine Safety and Health Administration).
  - International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW), Dec 2009-present
    The International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW) is a labor union which represents workers in the electrical industry in the United States, Canada, Panama and several Caribbean island nations; particularly electricians, or Inside Wiremen, in the construction industry and linemen and other employees of public utilities. The union also represents some workers in the computer, telecommunications, broadcasting, and other fields related to electrical work. It was founded in 1891 shortly after homes and businesses in the United States began receiving electricity. The IBEW is affiliated with the AFL-CIO.
  - International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City, Sep 2007-present
    The District Council 9 New York is local branch of the International Union of Painters and Allied Trades, chartered in 1900. District Council 9 is an organization of painters, decorators, wall covers, drywall finishers, sign painters, metal polishers, bridge & structural steel painters, civil service painters, lead abatement workers, glaziers & architectural metal glassworkers, paint makers, paint makers and allied trades.
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT), Dec 2009-present
    The International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT) is a labor union in the United States and Canada. Formed in 1903 by the merger of several local and regional locals of teamsters, the union now represents a diverse membership of blue-collar and professional workers, notably truckers, in both the public and private sectors. The union had approximately 1.4 million members in 2008. Formerly known as the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen and Helpers of America, the IBT is a member of the Change to Win Federation and Canadian Labour Congress.
  - International Federation of Professional and Technical Engineers (IFPTE), Dec 2009-present
    Founded in 1918, the International Federation of Professional and Technical Engineers, AFL-CIO & CLC, represents more than 80,000 men and women in professional, technical, administrative and associated occupations, representing employees in a wide variety of occupations in the federal, public, and private sectors.
  - International Labor Communications Association, Feb 2007-present
    The International Labor Communications Association (ILCA), founded in 1955, is the professional organization of labor communicators in North America. ILCA membership is open to national, regional, and local union publications and to media productions affiliated with the AFL-CIO and the CLC. The ILCA works to strengthen and expand labor print publications, websites, and radio, television, and film productions by providing resources, expertise, and networking opportunities for labor communicators.
  - International Longshore and Warehouse Union (ILWU), Dec 2009-present
    The International Longshore and Warehouse Union (ILWU) is a labor union which primarily represents dock workers on the West Coast of the United States, Hawaii and Alaska, and in British Columbia, Canada. It also represents hotel workers in Hawaii, cannery workers in Alaska, warehouse workers throughout the West and bookstore workers in Portland, Oregon. The union was established in 1937 after the 1934 West Coast Waterfront Strike, a 3-month-long strike that culminated in a 4-day general strike in San Francisco, California, and the Bay Area. The ILWU is affiliated with the Inland Boatmen's Union of the Pacific.
  - International Longshoremen's Association (ILA), Dec 2009-present
    Organized in 1892, the International Longshoremen's Association (ILA), AFL-CIO represents maritime workers in North America, representing upwards of 65,000 longshoremen on the Atlantic and Gulf Coasts, Great Lakes, major U.S. rivers, Puerto Rico and Eastern Canada. The union is also affiliated with the International Transport Workers' Federation, the International Organization of Masters, Mates and Pilots; the United Marine Division Tugboat Workers, and the officers of the New York State Supreme Court Officers are also affiliated with the ILA.
  - International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers (BAC), Dec 2009-present
    Bricklayers and Allied Craftsworkers (BAC) Local 7, established in 1994, was formed from seven BAC locals. Local 7, and is part of the International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers which, represents craftworkers in the trowel trades. BAC Local 7 represents workers in the New York and New Jersey area.
  - International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers. Local 7 (New York and New Jersey), May 2009-present
    Founded in 1865, the International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers represents craftworkers in the trowel trades across the United States and Canada including bricklayers, stone and marble masons, cement masons, plasterers, tilesetters, terrazzo and mosaic workers, and pointers/cleaners/caulkers.
  - International Union of Elevator Constructors (IUEC), Dec 2009-present
    The International Union of Elevator Constructors (IUEC) is a trade union in the United States and Canada of individuals who construct, modernize, repair, and service elevators, escalators, moving walkways, and other conveyances. The IUEC claims a membership of over 25,000 and was founded in 1901.
  - International Union of Operating Engineers (IUOE), Dec 2009-present
    The International Union of Operating Engineers (IUOE) represents primarily construction workers who work as heavy equipment operators, mechanics, surveyors, and stationary engineers (also called operating engineers or power engineers) who maintain heating and other systems in buildings and industrial complexes. Founded in 1896, it currently represents roughly 400,000 workers in approximately 170 local unions and operates nearly 100 apprenticeship programs. IUOE also represents nurses and other health industry workers, a significant number of public employees engaged in a wide variety of occupations, as well as a number of job classifications in the petrochemical industry.
  - International Union of Painters and Allied Trades, Apr 2012-present
    Founded in 1887, the International Union of Painters and Allied Trades, represents men and women in North America who work in the Finishing Trades of commercial and industrial painting, drywall finishing, glazing, floor covering, sign and trade show/convention display. The union is made up of 160,000 members. The website contains information on training sessions, publications, and their children’s foundation.
  - International Union of Police Associations (IUPA), Dec 2009-present
    The International Union of Police Associations (IUPA), founded in 1954, is an AFL-CIO chartered union for law enforcement, corrections, and law enforcement support personnel. IUPA works to support legislation that protects and affects public safety officers. Some legislative initiatives include the National Police Officers Bill of Rights, Fair Labor Standards Act (FLSA) for public employees, educational survivor benefits and armor vest grants.
  - International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America (UAW), Sep 2007-present
    The International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America also known as the United Auto Workers (UAW), founded in 1935, is a trade union that represents workplaces ranging from multinational corporations, small manufacturers and state and local governments to colleges and universities, hospitals and private non-profit organizations. UAW members work in industries as diverse as automobile and parts manufacturing, health care, casino gaming and higher education. The UAW has more than 750 local unions, with 390,000 active members and more than 600,000 retired members in the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico.
  - International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America (UAW) Local 2110, Mar 2009-present
    The Technical, Office and Professional (TOP) Union, Local 2110, is an amalgamated union with contracts covering workers in universities, publishing, museums, law firms and other offices, including teachers, secretaries, administrators, editors, computer operators, librarians, museum curators, typesetters and graphic artists. They promote benefits such as childcare, flex-time, job classification, domestic partner benefits and family leave. They are affiliated with the UAW and AFL-CIO.
  - Jewish Labor Committee, Mar 2009-present
    The Jewish Labor Committee, an independent secular organization, is the voice of the Jewish community in the labor movement and the voice of the labor movement in the Jewish community. The JLC was formed in 1934 by Yiddish-speaking immigrant trade union leaders and leaders of such groups as the Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring, the Jewish Labor Bund, and the United Hebrew Trades, in response to the rise of Nazism in Germany. The JLC enables the Jewish community and the trade union movement to work together on important issues of shared interest and concern, in pursuit of economic and social justice.
  - Jobs With Justice, Feb 2007-present
    Jobs with Justice, founded in 1987, is a national network of local coalitions that bring together labor unions, faith groups, community organizations, and student activists who fight for working people through long-term multi-issue coalition building, grassroots base-building, organizing, and strategic militant action. Jobs with Justice coalitions also worked on 127 community campaigns on issues like jobs and the economy, health care, immigrants' rights, global justice, accountable development, and sweat-free ordinances.
  - The Kid from Hoboken, Jul 2012
    This website contains the Kid from Hoboken series, the autobiography of Bill Bailey (1911–1995). Bill Bailey was a veteran of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and labor activist.
  - Labor and Working Class History Association, Oct 2009-present
    The Labor and Working Class History Association (LAWCHA) is an organization of historians, labor educations, and working class activists who seek to promote public and scholarly awareness of labor and working class history through research, writing, and organizing. The organization also promotes labor and working class history put into history and social studies curricula in public schools, colleges, and universities. LAWCHA gives grants and prizes to graduate students. The LAWCHA also publishes the journal, Labor: Studies in Working-Class History of the Americas.
  - Labor Arts, Sep 2007-present
    Labor Arts was created in 2000 by Donald Rubin, Evelyn Jones Rich, Moe Foner (1915-2002), Henry Foner, Esther Cohen, Rachel Bernstein and Debra E. Bernhardt (1953-2001), initially sponsored by the Shelley and Donald Rubin Foundation, Bread and Roses, the cultural arm of the hospital workers' local 1199, Service Employees International Union (SEIU), and the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives/Tamiment Library at New York University. Labor Arts acts as a virtual museum to gather, identify, and display examples of the cultural and artistic history of working people and trade unions.
  - Labor Community Strategy Center, May 2011-present
    The Labor Community Strategy Center, founded in 1989, is a think tank for regional, national, and international movement building, based in Los Angeles. The Strategy Center works on campaigns, projects, and publications rooted in working class urban communities of color with a particular focus on civil rights, environmental justice, public health, global warming, and the criminal legal system. They work to build leadership, and organization among those who face discrimination and societal attack. The Strategy Center develops campaigns and demands to attempt to build a world without war, racism, and imperialism through radical and structural change. The organization runs Frontlines Press, which produces books, pamphlets, radio shows, and films.
  - Labor Express, Nov 2011-present
    Labor Express, created in 1993 by former SEIU organizer Wayne Heimbach, as part of the programming on WLUW, 88.7 FM. Labor Express is a Chicago-based radio program on labor news and current events. They cover local, national, and international news on living wage jobs, healthcare, education, immigrant rights, the environment, and issues of race and gender. The program is a production of the Committee for Labor Access.
  - Labor Heritage Foundation, Sep 2007-present
    The Labor Heritage Foundation (LHF) which was founded in 1983, works to preserve and promote knowledge of the cultural heritage of the American worker through the arts, including music, poetry, written works, theatre, and artistic works; and conducts historical research through written and oral histories. LHF’s mission is to strengthen the labor movement through arts and music. LHF affiliates include, the LHF Catalogue (print and online catalogue of art related to the labor movement), the Great Labor Arts Exchange conference, awards, and other conferences.
  - Labor History Links Home Page, Oct 2011-present
    This site is a comprehensive bibliography of information, documents and links relating to U.S. labor history. It was developed by labor historian Rosemary Feurer for the Labor and Working Class History Association.
  - Labor Network for Sustainability, May 2012-present
    Labor Network for Sustainability (LNS) is a labor network dedicated to engaging trade unions, workers and allies to support economic, social, and environmental sustainability. The organization addresses issues such as climate protection, food security, economic justice, corporate accountability, water availability to renewable energy. The website contains information on issues, joining the network, blog posts, and the Green Workers Alliance.
  - Labor Notes, Feb 2007-present
    Labor Notes, founded in 1979, is a non-profit organization and network for rank-and-file union members and grassroots labor activists. Though officially titled the Labor Education and Research Project, the project is best known by the title of its monthly magazine. The magazine, both print and online, reports on news and analysis about labor activity or problems facing the labor movement. In its pages it advocates for a revitalization of the labor movement through Social Movement Unionism and union democracy. [Labor Notes is widely believed to have been an initiative of the International Socialist Organization, a Trotskyist group with organizations in the United States and other countries.]
  - Labor Press, Oct 2009-present
    Labor Press is an organization that includes a news, public relations, and promotional service for the New York labor community. Labor Press also maintains a website on current labor, building trades, retail, education, health and safety, and environmental issues. Labor Press produces newsletters, publications, websites, and targeted campaign materials for unions.
  - LaborBeat.org, Feb 2007-present
    Labor Beat, aka the Chicago-based Committee for Labor Access (CLA), founded in 1987, advocates for labor’s rank-and-file to have its own media and produce their own labor television and radio shows and news clips. CLA develops and distributes progressive television, radio, videos, and Internet communications on unions and workers issues. They are affiliated with Local 1220 of the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers.
  - Laborers' International Union of North America, Apr 2012-present
    Laborers’ International Union of North America (LIUNA), founded in 1903, is a union of semi-skilled construction workers. The union consists of a half million workers. The union supports workers through collective bargaining agreements, which earn family-supporting pay, good benefits and the opportunity for advancement. The website contains information on the structure of the union, press releases, and other information about the union.
  - LaborFest, Aug 2012-present
    LaborFest, established in 1994, is a labor, cultural, and film festival held annually in July in San Francisco. The festival was established in honor of the “Bloody Thursday” event and longshoremen and maritime workers strike in 1934. The website features schedules, videos, images, and other information on the current and previous years’ events. The website contains a schedule of events, which include film screenings, concerts, talks, and walking tours. The website also contains links and other multimedia.
  - LaborNet (U.S.), Feb 2007-present
    LaborNet, founded in 1991, is an organization created to build a democratic communication network for the labor movement and rebuild the labor movement with new technology. LaborNets are also established in the United Kingdom, Austria, Germany, Korea, Turkey, and Japan. LaborNet also works to defend the Internet from censorship and the privatization of information that would limit and destroy the rights to communicate and build world unionism. The website aggregates news related to the labor movement.
  - LaborTech, Nov 2010-present
    LaborTech brings together labor video, computer, and media activists to build and develop labor communications in technology and media. The website holds conferences (the first held in 1990) and campaigns to strengthen the labor movement.
  - Manumit School (1924-1957), Sep 2009-present
    The Manumit School was an “experimental boarding school in Pawling NY. Founded on purchased farm land in 1924 by William and Helen Fincke, it was formally call the Manumit School for Workers’ Children. An early promotional flyer for the school asked parents if they’d like their children to grow up “to become men and women who can think for themselves, stand on their own two feet and fight injustice and oppression. “ It’s teachings were meant to provide a “progressive “ “workers education” slant during a time of increasing socialist optimism in America. In 1944 the school moved to Bensalem Township, Bucks County, Pennsylvania. The school closed in 1957. This website is an informational website.
  - Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association (MEBA), Dec 2009-present